《霍比特人》
我警告过你
I warned you.
和矮人打交道不会有好下场
Did I not warn you what would come of dealing with Dwarves?
现在他们做了蠢事
Now they've done it.
弄醒了恶龙
They've woken the dragon!
厄运就要降临到我们头上
They've brought an apocalypse upon our heads!
快点 搞快点
Come on. Quickly.
快
Quickly.
再快点
Faster now...
我正忙着要撤离
...I'm trying to evacuate myself here.
小心点
Careful, man.
别管那些书了 把剩下的都搬走
Never mind the books. Get on, get the rest of it.
但镇长 难道我们不该想办法救小镇吗
But, sire, should we not try to save the town?
小镇救不了
The town is lost.
- 黄金要紧 - 你们都听见了 快点
- Save the gold! - You heard him. Get a move on.
- 爸爸 - 快
- Da! - Come on.
尽量堆高
Pile them up!
没有时间了 我们必须走
We have no time. We must leave.
- 把他扶起来 - 快点 弟弟
- Get him up. - Come on, brother.
- 快 快 我们走 - 我没事 自己能走
- Come on. Come on. Let's go. - I'm fine. I can walk.
- 尽可能跑快点 - 我们不走
- Fast as you can. - We're not leaving.
不能丢下爸爸
Not without our father.
如果你留在这里 你妹妹必死无疑
If you stay here, your sisters will die.
你父亲不会希望这种事发生吧
Is that what your father would want?
快把门打开
Open this door!
有人听见吗
Do you hear me?
我能看见它
I can see him!
看
Look!
下面来 快点
Down here! Now!
- 把手给我 - 快点 我们得走了
- Give me your hand. - Come on. We gotta go.
快点 赶快
Quickly now. Hurry.
奇力 快来
Kili, come on!
- 就在前面转角 - 继续前进
- It's around the corner! - Keep on going, man!
恶龙
Dragon!
快 快
Come on, come on!
划快点 再快点
Faster! Faster!
要是能多载些人就好了
If only we could take more of these people with us,
但他们的命…
...but they're hardly...
- 不值钱 我非常赞同 - 救命
- Worth it. I quite agree. - Help!
救命
Help!
小心
Look out!
快划
Move it!
快点 再快点
Come on! Faster!
我的金子 金子
My gold! My gold!
船承载不了这么多重量
We're carrying too much.
必须丢掉一些东西
We need to dump something.
说得对 阿尔弗雷德
Quite right, Alfrid.
快 快
Faster! Faster!
可怜的人们
Poor souls.
爸爸
Da.
Da!
他射中了
He hit it!
- 他射中恶龙了 - 没有
- He hit the dragon! - No.
他射中了 射出了划痕 我看见了
He did! He hit his mark! I saw.
他的箭射不穿龙鳞
His arrows cannot pierce its hide.
恐怕那龙坚不可摧
I fear nothing will.
你要做什么
What are you doing?
- 快回来 贝恩 - 贝恩
- Come back! Bain! - Bain!
贝恩
Bain!
快回到这里来
Get back here!
- 贝恩 - 让他去吧
- Bain! - Leave him.
我们不能回去
We cannot go back.
贝恩
Bain!
爸
Dad.
贝恩 你来做什么
Bain! What are you doing?
你应该离开的
Why didn't you leave, you were supposed to leave!
- 我来帮助你 - 不
- I came to help you. - No!
没什么能阻挡它了
Nothing can stop it now.
也许这个可以
This might.
贝恩
Bain.
你快回去
You go back.
快点离开这里
You get out of here. Now.
爸爸
Dad!
不
No!
爸爸
Dad!
停 停 不要动
Stop, stop! Halt!
别动
Halt!
是谁
Who are you...
那么大胆 竟敢来阻挡我
...that would stand against me?
真是遗憾
Now, that is a pity.
现在你该怎么办
What will you do now...
弓箭手
...Bowman?
你被抛弃了
You are forsaken.
没人会来帮助你
No help will come.
机会来了 快逃
Now's our chance! Go fled!
快逃到空旷的水域
Head for the open water!
嗯
Hmm.
那是你的孩子吧
Is that your child?
你无法从烈焰中救出他
You cannot save him from the fire.
我要把他烧焦
He will burn!
不要动 儿子
Stay still, son.
稳住
Stay still.
告诉我
Tell me...
可怜的贱民
...wretch...
你现在要怎么挑战我
...how now shall you challenge me?
你面前
You have nothing left...
只有死路一条
...but your death!
贝恩
Bain.
看着我
Look at me.
看着我就好
You look at me.
往左移一点
Little to your left.
就是这样
That's it.
贝恩 抓紧了
Bain! Hold on!
那是怎么了
What was that?
- 发生了什么事 - 它掉下去了 我看见了
- What happened? - It fell. I saw it.
它死了
It's dead.
史矛革死了
Smaug is dead.
我以胡子保证 他说对了
By my beard... I think he's right.
快看那里
Look there!
埃尔波尔的渡鸦飞回山里来了
The Ravens of Erebor are returning to the Mountain.
是啊
Aye.
消息很快就会传开
Word will spread.
用不了多久
Before long...
中土的人都会知道
...every soul in Middle-earth will know...
恶龙死了
...the dragon is dead!
《五军之战》
你并不孤单
You are not alone...
米斯兰达
...Mithrandir.
如果需要帮助 我一定会出现
救我
Help me!
我的孩子在哪
Where's my baby?
拜托
Please!
快来人救救我
Somebody help me!
救命啊
Help!
在那
Over there!
爸爸
Da!
- 爸爸 - 爸爸
- Da! - Da!
啊 为什么是我
Aah! Why me?
塔瑞尔
Tauriel.
奇力
Kili!
快过来
Come on.
我们要走了
We're leaving!
他们是你的同胞 你得走了
They are your people. You must go.
跟我一起走吧
Come with me.
我知道我的感受 我不在乎
I know how I feel. I'm not afraid.
你让我感觉生气蓬勃
You make me feel alive.
- 我不能 - 塔瑞尔
- I can't. - Tauriel.
我爱你
我不知道那是什么意思
I don't know what that means.
我想你知道
I think you do.
莱戈拉斯殿下
离开那矮人吧
你有自己的任务
再试一次
One more!
拿着它
Keep it.
当做信物
As a promise.
这有干毯子 你会需要的
These are dry. You'll need them.
- 谢谢你 - 给
- Thank you. - Here.
喂 给我拿一件
Oi! Give me one of them.
不然我会被冻死的
I'll catch my death in this cold.
你自己去找
Find your own!
现在不是你说了算 马屁精阿尔弗雷德
You're not in charge, Alfrid Lickspittle.
这你就说错了
You are wrong.
当镇长不在的时候
In the absence of the Master...
由镇长的副手 也就是本人
...the power cedes to his deputy...
代替他行使权利
...which in this instance is my good self.
把毯子给我
Now give me that blanket!
镇长的副手
Master's deputy?
别不要脸了
Don't make me laugh.
你就是个窃贼
You're a sneak-thief.
打死我也不会听你这种人的话
I'll be dead before I answer to you.
那就别怪我不客气了
Maybe that can be arranged.
要我就不会在这里胡闹 阿尔弗雷德 尤其是现在
I wouldn't go turning on your own, Alfrid. Not now.
- 爸 - 快过来
- Da! - Come here!
你还活着
You're alive.
没事了 宝贝
It's all right, darling.
是巴德 是他杀了恶龙
It was Bard! He killed the dragon!
我亲眼看见的
I saw it with me own eyes.
他把那个畜生杀死了
He brought the beast down!
用一支黑箭射死的
Shot him dead with a Black Arrow.
谢谢你 巴德
Thank you, Bard!
- 好样的 - 谢谢
- Good man. - Thank you!
你救了我们所有人
You've saved us all!
上天保佑你
Bless you.
向屠龙者致敬
All hail to the Dragon-Slayer!
向国王
All hail...
巴德致敬
...King Bard!
我说过很多次
I have said it many times.
他出生贵族世家
This is a man of noble stock.
- 天生的领袖 - 不要那样叫我
- A born leader! - Do not call me that.
我不是长湖镇镇长
I'm not Master of this town.
他在哪里
Where is he?
- 镇长在哪里 - 之前在去安都因河的路上
- Where's the Master? - Halfway down the Anduin.
带着我们所有的财宝 毫无疑问
With all our coin, I don't doubt.
你肯定知道
You would know.
是你帮他搬运的财宝
You helped him empty the treasury.
没有
No.
我试图拦住他
I tried to stop him.
- 骗子 - 小偷
- Liar! - Cheat!
你个狗杂种
You're a mongrel!
我恳请他 哀求他
I begged. I pleaded.
放逐他吧
Away with him!
- 烧死他 - 我说 "镇长"
- Tar him! - I said, "Master"...
"这样不对"
..."No"!
"为孩子们想想"
"Think of the children."
绞死他
Hang him!
"你们都不为孩子想想吗"
"Will nobody think of the children?"
嗷
Ow!
把他挂在树上
To the tree with him!
- 绞死他 - 把他带走
- Hang him hard! - Take him down!
够了 放开他
Enough! Let him go!
放开他
Let him go!
看看你们周围
Look around you!
难道你们 还嫌死得人不够多吗
Have you not had your fill of death?
凛冬将至
Winter is upon us.
我们不仅要照顾自己
We must look to our own.
还有病人和无家可归的人
To the sick and the helpless.
还能走动的人去照料伤者
Those who can stand, tend to the wounded.
力气大的人跟我来
Those who have strength, follow me.
我们必须尽最大努力抢救
We must salvage what we can.
然后怎么办 之后我们做什么
What then? What'll we do then?
寻找庇护所
We find shelter.
有人吗
Hello!
邦博
Bombur?
波佛
Bofur?
有人吗
Anybody?
等等
Wait!
- 是比尔博 - 他还活着
- It's Bilbo! - He's alive!
停 停下
Stop! Stop!
停下
Stop.
你们必须离开
You need to leave.
我们都得离开
We all need to leave.
我们才刚到这里来呢
We only just got here.
我跟他说过 但他不听劝告
I've tried talking, but he won't listen.
- 你这话什么意思 伙计 - 是索林
- What do you mean, laddie? - Thorin!
索林 索林 他下去有几天了
Thorin. Thorin. He's been down there for days.
不睡觉 不吃饭
He doesn't sleep. He barely eats.
他都快变了一个人 这还不算什么
He's not been himself. Not at all.
这个地方这个地方 我觉得有种邪气
It's this... It's this place. Ahem. I think a sickness lies on it.
邪气
Sickness?
哪种邪气
What kind of sickness?
菲力
Fili.
Fili!
菲力
黄金
Gold.
数之不尽的黄金
Gold beyond measure.
没有痛苦
Beyond sorrow...
没有哀伤
...and grief.
请看
Behold...
伟大的
...the great...
索尔留下的巨大宝藏
...treasure hoard of Thror.
欢迎
Welcome...
我的外甥们
...my sister-sons...
来到埃尔波尔
...to the Kingdom...
王国
...of Erebor.
巴林
Balin!
奇力
Kili!
感谢都灵 你们还活着
Thank Durin, you're alive.
庞博
Bombur!
你还活着
You're alive!
- 有什么发现吗 - 这边没有
- Any sign of it? - Nothing yet.
这边也没用
Nothing here.
- 继续找 - 宝石可能会在任何地方
- Keep searching! - That jewel could be anywhere.
阿肯宝石肯定还在这里面
The Arkenstone is in these halls.
- 找到它 - 你听到了
- Find it! - You heard him.
- 快找 - 都去找
- Keep looking. - All of you!
找到之前不许休息
No one rests until it is found.
我差点都想让你拿走宝石
I am almost tempted to let you take it.
只为了能看到橡木盾饱受其折磨
If only to see Oakenshield suffer.
看着宝石摧毁他
Watch it destroy him.
看着钻石腐蚀他的心智
Watch it corrupt his heart.
让他疯掉
...and drive him mad.
我来帮你
I've got you.
只带必需品
Take only what you need.
我们还有很远的路要走
We have a long march ahead.
你们要到哪去
Where will you go?
只有一个地方可去
There is only one place.
孤山
The Mountain.
你可真英明 大人
You are a genius, sire.
我们可以在山里避难
We can take refuge inside the Mountain.
虽然会有恶龙的气味 但女人们可以打扫干净
It might smell a bit of dragon, but the women can clean that up.
那里将会很安全 暖和 干燥
It'll be safe and warm and dry...
物资丰富
...and full of stores...
有床和衣物
...bedding, clothing...
还有一些黄金
...the odd bit of gold.
山里的黄金都被诅咒了
What gold is in that Mountain is cursed.
我们只取应得的那份
We will take only what was promised to us.
只拿用来重建家园和维持生活的
Only what we need to rebuild our lives.
来 你再多拿点
Here. Pull your weight.
史矛革的死讯很快会传遍整片大陆
News of the death of Smaug will have spread through the lands.
没错
Aye.
会有人觊觎孤山的
Others will now look to the Mountain...
财富
...for its wealth...
以及它的有利地形
...for its position.
你还知道什么
What is it you know?
都不确定
Nothing for certain.
都是我的猜测
It's what I fear may come.
林地精灵
精灵国王的儿子和一个女精灵
跟踪我们到了长湖镇
那你把他们都杀了吗
他们像胆小鬼一样
尖叫着逃跑了
蠢货 他们还会回来的
到时候会带着精灵军队
速去冈达巴
让各军团出动
精灵
人类
矮人
孤山将会是他们的坟墓
开战
你在那边看见什么了
You saw something out there.
追到长湖镇的半兽人军团 我知道是谁了
The Orc I pursued out of Lake-town, I know who he is.
博尔格 毁灭者阿索格的儿子
Bolg, spawn of Azog the Defiler.
一群座狼在长湖镇外等着他
A Warg pack was waiting for him on the outskirts of Esgaroth.
他们逃往北方去了
They fled into the North.
这些半兽人和其他以前的不一样
These Orcs were different from the others.
他们的标记 我已经很久没有看到过了
They bore a mark I have not seen for a long time.
冈达巴的标记
The mark of Gundabad.
冈达巴
Gundabad?
远离迷雾山脉北方的一个半兽人大本营
An Orc stronghold in the far North of the Misty Mountains.
莱格拉斯殿下
我带来了您父王的口信
他让您立即返回
走吧 塔瑞尔
殿下
塔瑞尔被放逐了
放逐
你回去告诉我父王
You may tell my father...
如果不让塔瑞尔回去 我也不回去
...if there is no place for Tauriel, there is no place for me.
莱戈拉斯
Legolas.
这是你父王的命令
It is your king's command.
没错 他是我的国王
但他的命令不能主宰我
我要去北方 你和我一起来吗
I ride North. Will you come with me?
到哪里去
To where?
冈达巴
To Gundabad.
万能的维拉 救救他吧
救救他吧
请听我说 解除他身上的咒语
解除他身上的咒语 不要让他死去
念咒语救不了你的 老东西
你身上有我主人要的东西
它在哪里
精灵三戒之一的
火之戒纳亚
其它两枚在哪里
这是我主人的地盘
你死到临头了 巫师
我为了米斯兰达而来
I come for mithrandir.
而且我要带走他
And I will leave with him.
如果你胆敢碍事 我就灭了你
If you try to stop me, I will destroy you.
三枚戒指给了天空之下的精灵国王们
七枚戒指给了石厅里的矮人国王
九枚戒指
Nine...
给了注定死亡的人类
...for mortal Men doomed to die.
你无法和影子战斗
更何况你很虚弱
独自一人
孤掌难鸣
我不是独自一人
I am not alone.
夫人 需要帮忙吗
Are you in need of assistance, my lady?
你该乖乖长眠地下
You should've stayed dead.
米斯兰达
Mithrandir...
醒醒
...come back.
他在这里
He is here.
是的
Yes.
黑暗已经再度降临了
The darkness has returned.
快点
Go on.
甘道夫
Gandalf!
快上车
Climb on!
他很虚弱
He is weak.
不能呆在这里了 这里会消耗他的生命
He cannot remain here. It is draining his life.
走
Go!
快点
Quickly!
和我一起走 夫人
Come with me, my lady.
快走
Go!
已经开始了
东方将会陨落
安格玛王国将会崛起
精灵的时代已经结束了
半兽人的时代即将来临
轮不到你
You have no...
在这放肆
...power here...
魔苟斯之仆
...servant of Morgoth.
你只是无名鼠辈
You are nameless.
无脸无形
Faceless.
行尸走肉
Formless.
滚回太虚中去吧
Go back to the void...
那是你本该待的地方
...from whence you came!
我们被欺骗了
索伦依旧阴魂不散
The spirit of Sauron endured.
他已经被驱逐了
And has been banished.
他会逃往东方
He will flee into the East.
必须给刚铎发去警告
Gondor should be warned.
他们肯定监视着魔多的动静
They must set a watch on the walls of Mordor.
不
No.
照顾好凯兰崔尔夫人
Look after the Lady Galadriel.
她耗费了太多的力量
She has spent much of her power.
快撑不住了
Her strength is failing.
带她到罗斯洛立安城
Take her to Lothlórien.
萨鲁曼大人
My Lord Saruman.
我们必须乘胜追击
He must be hunted down...
摧毁他 不留后患
...and destroyed once and for all.
没有那枚指环的力量
Without the Ring of Power...
索伦就永远没法卷土重来 染指中土
...Sauron can never again hold dominion over Middle-earth.
你们快走
Go now.
索伦的事交给我
Leave Sauron to me.
- 我要一匹马 - 什么
- I need a horse. - What?
甘道夫
Gandalf...
- 你要到哪里去 - 警告埃尔波尔
- ...where are you going? - To warn Erebor.
他们不清楚将要到发生的事
They have no idea what is coming.
我亲眼看见成千上万的莫瑞亚半兽人
I saw them with my own eyes, rank upon rank of Moria Orcs.
你得去召集我们的朋友 鹰王和人熊
You must summon our friends, bird and beast.
孤山大战就要来了
The battle for the Mountain is about to begin.
等等
Wait.
拿上这个
Take this.
如果你说的是真的 那么你比我更需要这个
If what you say is true, then you'll need it more than I.
谢谢你
Thank you.
提醒你一点
A word of warning, eh?
这玩意有时候不太灵敏
It can be a bit dicky sometimes.
到时候你只需要拧一拧杖头就好
You just have to twiddle with the top.
我想你知道怎样做
I expect you'll manage.
它就在这些大厅里
It is here in these halls.
我很确定
I know it.
我们四处都找过了
We have searched and searched.
还不够
Not well enough.
索林 我们都很想找回宝石
Thorin, we all would see the stone returned.
但是就是找不到
And yet, it is still not found!
你是在怀疑我们对你的的忠诚
Do you doubt the loyalty of anyone here?
阿肯宝石
The Arkenstone...
是我族人的传承之宝
...is the birthright of our people.
它是国王的宝石
It is The King's Jewel.
难道我不是国王吗
Am I not the king?
听好了
Know this:
如果有谁找到宝石
If anyone should find it...
却私藏起来
...and withhold it from me...
我必将严惩
...I will be avenged.
恶龙附体了
Dragon-sickness.
我之前见过
I've seen it before.
那种表情
That look.
过度的欲望
The terrible need.
对财宝强烈而病态的追求 比尔博
It is a fierce and jealous love, Bilbo.
曾经把他的祖父逼疯
It sent his grandfather mad.
巴林 如果索林
Balin, if Thorin...
得到了阿肯宝石
...had the Arkenstone...
我是说如果找到了
...or if it was found...
会对他有帮助吗
...would it help?
那个宝石象征着皇权
That stone crowns all.
谁握有宝石
It is the summit of this great wealth...
就能掌控大权和所有财富
...bestowing power upon he who bears it.
他会就此打住吗
Would it stay his madness?
不 孩子
No, laddie.
恐怕他会变得更糟
I fear it would make him worse.
也许这宝石
Perhaps it is best...
还是别被找到的好
...it remains lost.
那是什么
What is that?
你手里的东西
In your hand.
没什么
It's nothing.
给我看看
Show me.
这是
It...
我在比翁的花园里捡的
I picked it up in Beorn's garden.
你这一路一直带着
You've carried it all this way?
我要把它种在我的花园里
I'm gonna plant it in my garden.
袋底洞边上
In Bag End.
这作为带回夏尔的战利品也太不起眼了
It's a poor prize to take back to the Shire.
有一天它会长大
One day, it'll grow.
每当我看到它 就会想起
And every time I look at it, I'll remember.
想起所有发生过的事 好的 不好的
Remember everything that happened, the good, the bad...
还有多幸运能活着回家
...and how lucky I am that I made it home.
索林 我
Thorin, I...
索林
Thorin.
长湖镇的幸存者
Survivors from Lake-town...
都在涌向河谷镇
...they're streaming into Dale.
数以百计的难民
There's hundreds of them.
叫所有人到大门处集合
Call everyone to the gate.
到大门那
To the gate!
立刻
Now!
快点
Come on.
- 继续走 - 大人
- Keep moving. - Sire!
大人
Sire!
快上来
Up here!
大人快看 火盆点起来了
Look, sire! The braziers are lit.
看来
So...
索林·橡木盾他们还活着
...the Company of Thorin Oakenshield survived.
还活着
Survived?
你是说那群矮人和满屋的黄金在一起
You mean there's a bunch of Dwarves with all that gold?
不用担心 阿尔弗雷德
I shouldn't worry, Alfrid.
孤山里的黄金多得很
There's gold enough in that Mountain for all.
今晚在这里过夜
Make camp here tonight!
自己去找留宿的地方
Find what shelter you can.
升几堆火
Get some fires going.
- 快点 快去 - 阿尔弗雷德
- Come on, hurry along now. - Alfrid.
你今晚负责守夜
You'll take the night watch.
堆上去
Up it goes!
就是这样
That's it.
我要堡垒在天亮之前堆好
I want this fortress made safe by sunup.
夺回孤山实属不易
This Mountain was hard-won.
我不会让它再次被夺走
I will not see it taken again.
长湖镇的难民一无所有
The people of Lake-town have nothing.
他们前来求助
They came to us in need.
他们失去了一切
They have lost everything.
不要告诉我他们失去了什么
Do not tell me what they have lost.
我理解他们的艰难
I know well enough their hardship.
那些在恶龙之火中活下来的人应该值得庆幸
Those who have lived through dragon fire should rejoice.
他们应该心存感激
They have much to be grateful for.
多弄点石头
More stone.
门口的石头再多点
Bring more stone to the gate!
就这样
That's it.
- 孩子们正挨着饿 - 我们需要食物
- These children are starving. - We need food.
- 我们最多坚持三天 - 巴德
- We won't last three days. - Bard...
- 我们物资匮乏 - 尽你所能 珀西
- ...we don't have enough. - Do what you can, Percy.
- 没事的 - 不要担心
- It'll be all right. - Don't worry.
我们需要更多的水
We need more water.
孩子 受伤的人还有妇女先过来
The children, the wounded and the women come first.
给
Here you are.
早上好 阿尔弗雷德
Good morning, Alfrid.
夜里有没有什么动静
What news from the night watch?
很安静 大人 没什么可汇报的
All quiet, sire. Not much to report.
连鬼影都没来过
Nothing gets past me.
除了一支精灵军队
Except an army of Elves, it would seem.
瑟兰迪尔陛下 没想到您
My Lord Thranduil, we did not look...
- 会大驾光临 - 听说你需要帮助
- ...to see you here. - I heard you needed aid.
接着
Here you go.
向后传
Pass it back.
这还有
Another one.
你救了我们
You have saved us.
我都不知道怎么报答你
I do not know how to thank you.
你不需要感激
Your gratitude is misplaced.
我不是专为你们而来
I did not come on your behalf.
我是来取回属于我的东西
I came to reclaim something of mine.
那山里也有我想要的宝石
There are gems in the Mountain that I, too, desire.
散发着纯白星光的珠宝
White gems of pure starlight.
绿叶森林的白宝石
The White Gems of Lasgalen.
我知道有位精灵王愿出高价交换这些宝石
I know an Elf Lord who will pay a pretty price for these.
等等 请等一下
Wait! Please wait!
为了一些宝石你就要去打仗
You would go to war over a handful of gems?
我们族人的国宝岂能容他人占有
The heirlooms of my people are not lightly forsaken.
这点咱们在同一战线上
We are allies in this.
山里的财宝 我们的人也应得一份
My People also have a claim upon the riches in that Mountain.
让我去和索林谈谈
Let me speak with Thorin.
你想和矮人讲道理
You would try to reason with the Dwarf?
为了避免挑起战争
To avoid war?
没错
Yes.
辛苦了一晚 做得不错
Not a bad night's work.
都过来
Come on.
索恩之子 索林万岁
Hail, Thorin, son of Thrain.
看到你们还活着 我们很高兴
We are glad to find you alive beyond hope.
你为何带着军队
Why do you come to the gates...
来城门下讨敌叫阵
...of the King under the Mountain armed for war?
那为何孤山国王躲在城墙后面
Why does the King under the Mountain fence himself in...
像个缩在洞里的强盗
...like a robber in his hold?
或许是因为我担心有人来抢劫
Perhaps it is because I am expecting to be robbed.
国王陛下
My lord...
我们不会抢劫你
...we have not come to rob you...
我是来解决问题的
...but to seek fair settlement.
能跟我谈谈吗
Will you not speak with me?
我洗耳恭听
I am listening.
我代表长湖镇的人民
On behalf of the people of Lake-town...
要求您履行承诺
...I ask that you honor your pledge.
和他们分享财宝
A share of the treasure...
好让他们能够重建家园
...so that they might rebuild their lives.
我不会跟任何...
I will not treat with any man...
挟着大军压境的人讨价还价
...while an armed host lies before my door.
要是我们不能达成协议 大军就会攻打孤山
That armed host will attack this Mountain if we do not come to terms.
你的威胁并不能使我动摇
And your threats do not sway me.
你的良心何在
What of your conscience?
难道我们的请求不是理所应当的吗
Does it not tell you our cause is just?
我的人民帮助过你
My people offered you help.
而你却带给他们的死亡和毁灭作为回报
And in return, you brought upon them only ruin and death.
长湖镇的人难道不是为了丰厚的报酬才帮我们
When did Lake-town come to our aid but for the promise of rich reward?
那是公平的交易
A bargain was struck!
交易
A bargain?
我们除了拿祖传宝藏
What choice did we have but to barter our birthright...
去交换毛毯和食物
...for blankets and food?
好争取自由换取未来 还能怎么办
To ransom our future in exchange for our freedom?
你说那是公平的交易
You call that a fair trade?
告诉我
Tell me...
屠龙者巴德
...Bard the Dragon-Slayer...
我为什么要遵守这样的约定
...why should I honor such terms?
因为你给过我们承诺
Because you gave us your word.
难道这承诺一文不值
Does that mean nothing?
走开
Be gone!
不然我就要放箭了
Ere our arrows fly!
你在做什么
What are you doing?
你不能挑起战争
You cannot go to war.
- 这和你没关系 - 不好意思
- This does not concern you. - Excuse me...
防止你没注意到 我得提醒你外面有一支精灵大军
...but in case you haven't noticed, there is an army of Elves out there.
更别说有几百个愤怒的渔民
Not to mention several hundred angry fishermen.
我们实际上寡不敌众
We are, in fact, outnumbered.
不会太久的
Not for much longer.
这是什么意思
What does that mean?
意思是 巴金斯先生
It means, Master Baggins...
永远不要低估矮人
...you should never underestimate Dwarves.
我们能收复埃尔波尔
We have reclaimed Erebor.
现在
Now...
也能守住它
...we defend it.
他一毛不拔
He will give us nothing.
真可惜
Such a pity.
- 至少你试过了 - 我搞不明白
- Still you tried. - I do not understand.
为什么
Why?
为什么他宁愿挑起战争
Why would he risk war?
和他们讲理是白费力气
It is fruitless to reason with them.
他们现在只认这个
They understand only one thing.
我们在拂晓发动进攻
We attack at dawn.
你要和我们一起吗
Are you with us?
好
Aye.
巴金斯先生 过来
Master Baggins, come here.
你会用得着这个
You're going to need this.
穿上它
Put it on.
这件背心由银合金制成
This vest is made of silver steel.
秘银
Mithril...
我的祖先这样称呼它
...it was called by my forebears.
穿上它刀剑不入
No blade can pierce it.
看起来很滑稽
I look absurd.
我不是战士 只是个霍比特人
I'm not a warrior, I'm a Hobbit.
这是件礼物
It is a gift.
作为我们友谊的象征
A token of our friendship.
真朋友千金难求
True friends are hard to come by.
我以前看走了眼
I have been blind...
不过现在看清了
...but now I begin to see.
有人背叛了我
I am betrayed.
背叛
Betrayed?
阿肯宝石
The Arkenstone.
他们中有人拿去了
One of them has taken it.
他们中有人撒了谎
One of them is false.
索林
Thorin...
你的心愿已经实现 你夺回了孤山
...the Quest is fulfilled, you've won the Mountain.
这还不够吗
Is that not enough?
- 被自己的同胞背叛 - 不
- Betrayed by my own kin. - Now, uh...
你对长湖镇的人们许下承诺
...you made a promise to the people of Lake-town.
难道 财宝
Now, is this treasure...
真比自己的名誉还重要吗
...truly worth more than your honor?
我们的名誉 索林 我当时也帮你说了话
Our honor, Thorin. I was also there. I gave my word.
对于此事 我心存感激
For that, I am grateful.
那是高尚的表现 但是孤山的财宝
It was nobly done, but the treasure of this mountain...
并不属于长湖镇的
...does not belong to the people...
居民
...of Lake-town.
这些黄金
This gold...
是我们的
...is ours.
只能是我们的
And ours alone.
我用生命起誓
By my life...
我绝不舍弃
...I will not part...
任何金币
...with a single coin.
哪怕
Not...
一小块
...one..
也不会
...piece of it.
冈达巴山
Gundabad.
山里面有什么
What lies beyond?
一个宿敌
An old enemy.
古老的安格玛王国
The ancient kingdom of Angmar.
这些堡垒曾经是他们的大本营
This fortress was once its stronghold.
是他们补给装备
It is where they kept their great armories.
打造兵器的兵工厂
Forged their weapons of war.
有光 我看到人影走动
A light. I saw movement.
我们等天黑了再行动
We wait for the cover of night.
这个地方很凶险 塔瑞尔
It is a fell place, Tauriel.
上个世纪 我们的族人曾在这里血战
In another age, our people waged war on those lands.
我的母亲死在这里
My mother died there.
父王从不提起这件事
My father does not speak of it.
没有坟墓
There is no grave.
没有哀思
No memory.
什么都没有
Nothing.
让我过去
Let me through!
让开
Make Way!
不 不
No, no.
不 喂 你
No! Oi! You!
尖帽子那个
Pointy hat!
对
Yes.
就是你 我们不收流浪汉 乞丐
You. We don't want no tramps, beggars...
别在这里转悠
...nor vagabonds here.
我们的麻烦都已经够多了
We got enough trouble without the likes of you.
骑上你的马 快滚吧
Off you go. On your horse.
谁是这里管事的
Who's in charge here?
是谁在问
Who is asking?
你们和矮人的恩怨必须先放在一边
You must set aside your petty grievances with the Dwarves.
战争就要来了
War is coming!
多尔戈多的敌军倾巢而出
The cesspits of Dol Guldur have been emptied.
你们都处于危险之中
You're all in mortal danger.
你在说些什么
What are you talking about?
看得出你对巫师一无所知
I can see you know nothing of Wizards.
他们就像冬日的响雷
They are like winter thunder on a wild wind...
自远方随狂风而来 轰隆作响让人惊慌不已
...rolling in from a distance, breaking hard in alarm.
但往往只是雷声大雨点小
But sometimes a storm is just a storm.
这次不一样
Not this time.
半兽人军队正在路上
Armies of Orcs are on the move.
它们都是杀手 为战争而生
These are fighters. They have been bred for war.
我们的敌人动用了全部力量
Our enemy has summoned his full strength.
为什么它们现在才行动
Why show his hand now?
是我们逼的
Because we forced him.
自从索林·橡木盾一行人动身去收复孤山起开始的
We forced him when the Company of Thorin set out to reclaim their homeland.
它们绝不愿意看到矮人回到埃尔波尔
The Dwarves were never meant to reach Erebor.
毁灭者阿佐格奉命去追杀他们
Azog the Defiler was sent to kill them.
他的主人 想要掌控孤山
His master seeks control of the Mountain.
不仅是因为那里面的财宝
Not just for the treasure within...
还有孤山的战略位置 有利的地形
...but for where it lies, its strategic position.
这里是夺回北方古国安格玛的要塞
This is the gateway to reclaiming the lands of Angmar in the North.
如果那个失落的王国再度崛起
If that fell kingdom should rise again...
瑞文戴尔 罗瑞安 夏尔
...Rivendell, Lórien, the Shire...
甚至刚铎王国 也会陷落
...even Gondor itself, will fall.
你说的这些半兽人军队 米斯兰达
These Orc armies you speak of, Mithrandir...
现在在哪里
...where are they?
我们的军队将在黎明前完成布署
会打得他们措手不及
那些蠢货
早就忘记这片土地下的生物
忘记巨型地蛇的存在
如果要进去  现在就该行动了
它们蜂拥而出
这些蝙蝠的存在只为一个目的
These bats are bred for one purpose.
什么目的
For what?
战争
For war.
必须警告其他人
也许晚了  快走
来吧 我们把那些刀磨得锋利些
Come on, let's get those blades sharpened.
是啊 该死的精灵
Aye. Blasted Elves.
- 你用斧头砍了？- 没有
- You swing an ax at it? - No, brother.
你该待在屋里
You should be inside.
出来放风
Out of the wind.
不 我…
No, I...
出来透透气 这地儿龙的臭味太重
...needed some air. Place still stinks of dragon.
精灵大军的
The Elves have been moving...
- 弓箭手已经就位了 - 是啊
- ...their archers into position. - Ah.
明天战斗将见个分晓
The battle will be over by tomorrow's eve.
虽然我怀疑 我们会活到最后
Though I doubt we will live to see it.
这真是暗无天日啊
No, these are dark days.
确实是暗无天日
Dark days indeed.
嗯
Hmm.
即使你不想被困在这里 也没有人会责备你
No one could blame a soul for wishing themselves elsewhere.
已经快到午夜了
Must be nearing midnight.
邦博会接替巡查
Bombur's got the next watch.
我去叫醒他
It'll take a bit to wake him.
波佛
Bofur?
我们明天早上见
I will see you in the morning.
再见 比尔博
Goodbye, Bilbo.
什么时候起我的忠告变得一文不值
Since when has my counsel counted for so little?
你以为我想干嘛
What do you think I'm trying to do?
我想你只是在试图拯救你的矮人朋友
I think you try to save your Dwarvish friends,
我钦佩你对他们的忠诚
and I admire your loyalty to them.
但这不足以构成我停兵的理由
But it does not dissuade me from my course.
这一切由你而起 米斯兰达
You started this, Mithrandir.
你不介意由我来收尾吧
You will forgive me if I finish it.
弓箭手就位了吗
Are the archers in position?
- 是的 陛下 - 传我命令
- Yes, my lord. - Give the order.
若山上有任何风吹草动
If anything moves on that Mountain...
格杀勿论
...kill it.
矮人的大限已到
The Dwarves are out of time.
神箭手
Bowman!
你同意他说的话吗
Do you agree with this?
金子对你来说有那么重要吗
Is gold so important to you?
难道为了得到财宝不惜让矮人流血吗
Would you buy it with the blood of Dwarves?
不会发展到那一步的
It won't come to that.
- 这场仗他们赢不了 - 他们不会认输的
- This is a fight they cannot win. - That won't stop them.
你认为矮人会投降 不会
You think the Dwarves will surrender? They won't.
他们会为了家园战斗至死
They will fight to the death.
比尔博·巴金斯
Bilbo Baggins.
如果我没搞错
If I'm not mistaken...
这就是在我守卫的眼皮底下
...this is the Halfling who stole the keys...
偷走地牢钥匙的半身人吧
...to my dungeons from under the nose of my guards.
是的
Yes.
那件事很抱歉
Sorry about that.
我来
I came...
是给你们这个的
...to give you this.
孤山之心
The Heart of the Mountain.
王之珍宝
The King's Jewel.
足以让国王将其赎回
And worth a king's ransom.
你怎么能把它给我们
How is this yours to give?
我把它当作我十四分之一份额的报酬
I took it as my 14th share of the treasure.
你为什么这么做
Why would you do this?
你不欠我们什么
You owe us no loyalty.
我不是为了你们
I'm not doing it for you.
我知道矮人们非常顽固
I know that Dwarves can be obstinate...
执着
...and pigheaded...
难缠
...and difficult.
多疑 神神秘秘
They're suspicious and secretive...
你想象不到他们举止有多没礼貌
...with the worst manners you can possibly imagine,
但他们也不失勇敢
but they are also brave...
善良
...and kind...
而且非常忠诚
...and loyal to a fault.
我很喜欢他们 我想尽可能的去救他们
I've grown very fond of them, and I would save them if I can.
对索林来说
Now, Thorin...
他珍视这宝石胜过一切
...values this stone above all else.
为了宝石 我想他会归还属于你们的财宝
In exchange for its return, I believe he will give you what you are owed.
没有必要再去发动战争
There will be no need for war.
今晚好好休息
Rest up tonight.
- 明天一早就得离开 - 什么
- You must leave on the morrow. - What?
- 走得越远越好 - 我是不会离开的
- Get as far away from here as possible. - I'm not leaving.
你选我为这个集体的十四分之一 我现在还不想离开
You picked me as the 14th man. I'm not leaving the Company, now.
不再有什么集体了
There is no Company. Not anymore.
天知道索林发现你的行为后会做出什么事来
Imagine what Thorin will do when he finds out what you've done.
我不害怕索林
I'm not afraid of Thorin.
你应该害怕
Well, you should be.
不要低估了那些金子的邪恶
Don't underestimate the evil of gold.
尤其是恶龙长期盘踞过的金子
Gold over which a serpent has long brooded.
龙症会侵蚀每个靠近孤山的人的心灵
Dragon-sickness seeps into the hearts of all who come near this Mountain.
几乎无人幸免
Almost all.
你 过来
You there.
给这霍比特人找张床
Find this Hobbit a bed...
备好热饭让他饱餐一顿
...and fill his belly with hot food.
他应得的
He's earned it.
嗨
Hey.
暗中留意他
Keep an eye on him.
只要他试图离开 你立刻向我报告
If he should try to leave, you tell me.
快走
Move it!
愚蠢的霍比特人
Stupid Hobbit.
醒醒 醒醒 霍比特人 该起床了
Wakey-wakey, Hobbit. Up you...get.
下一箭会射中你的眉心
I will put the next one between your eyes.
我们前来告诉你
We have come to tell you...
你们偿还的欠款已经收到
...payment of your debt has been offered...
我们笑纳了
...and accepted.
什么欠款
What payment?
我什么都没给你们
I gave you nothing.
你们什么都没有
You have nothing.
我们有这个
We have this.
他们拿着阿肯宝石
They have the Arkenstone.
盗贼
Thieves!
你怎么会有我们祖传宝物
How came you by the heirloom of our house?
这宝石属于国王
That stone belongs to the king!
国王可以拿到它
And the king may have it...
我们也很乐意归还
...with our goodwill.
但首先他得兑现他的诺言
But first he must honor his word.
他们把我们当傻子
They are taking us for fools.
这是个骗局
This is a ruse.
肮脏的谎言
A filthy lie.
阿肯宝石还在山里
The Arkenstone is in this Mountain!
这是个诡计
It is a trick!
这不是诡计
It's no trick.
宝石是真的
The stone is real.
我给他们的
I gave it to them.
你
You?
我把它当作我应得的那份报酬
I took it as my 14th share.
是你从我这里偷走的
You would steal from me?
从你那偷走 不
Steal from you? No.
我也许是个飞贼 但我自认为是诚实的人
No, I may be a burglar, but I like to think I'm an honest one.
这是我应得的部分
I'll let it stand against my claim.
应得的部分
Against your claim?
你的权利
Your claim.
你无权凌驾于我之上 你这个卑鄙的鼠辈
You have no claim over me, you miserable rat!
我本来是准备交给你的
I was going to give it to you.
- 很多次都想 但是 - 但是 什么
- Many times I wanted to, but... - But what...
窃贼
...thief?
你变了 索林
You are changed, Thorin.
我在袋底洞认识的那个矮人 从不食言
The Dwarf I met in Bag End would never have gone back on his word.
也绝不会质疑族人对他的忠诚
Would never have doubted the loyalty of his kin!
你还跟我谈
Do not speak to me...
忠诚
...of loyalty.
把他从城墙上扔下去
Throw him from the rampart!
你们没有听到吗
Did you not hear me?
我亲自动手 我诅咒你
I will do it myself. Curse you!
不
No!
诅咒把你强加于
Cursed be the Wizard...
- 我们的巫师 - 如果你对我的飞贼不满意
- ...that forced you on us! - If you don't like my burglar...
请你
...then please...
不要伤害他
...don't damage him.
把他还给我
Return him to me.
你没给自己树立好山下国王正面的形象
You're not making a very splendid figure as King under the Mountain...
你说呢 索林 索恩之子
...are you, Thorin...son of Thrain?
我永远不会再与巫师做交易
Never again will I have dealings with Wizards!
- 快走 - 还有夏尔的鼠辈
- Go. - Or Shire rats!
可以谈判了吧
Are we resolved?
用阿肯宝石换取你的承诺
The return of the Arkenstone for what was promised?
为什么我要花钱买回 本来就属于我的东西？
Why should I buy back that which is rightfully mine?
留着宝石 卖掉算了
Keep the stone, sell it.
刚铎的执政宰相会给你开个好价的
Ecthelion of Gondor will give you a good price for it.
我要杀了你
I will kill you!
我发誓 我要干掉你们所有人
By my oath, I will kill you all!
你的誓言一毛不值
Your oath means nothing.
我听够了
I've heard enough.
索林 撤掉你的军队
Thorin, lay down your arms.
打开大门
Open these doors.
宝藏会害死你的
This treasure will be your death.
索林 我们赢不了这场战斗
Thorin, we cannot win this fight.
快给我们答案
Give us your answer.
你是选择和平
Will you have peace...
还是战争
...or war?
我选择战争
I will have war.
铁足丹恩
Ironfoot.
铜墙铁壁阵
嘿 索林
Hey, Thorin!
铁足军团赶到了
Ironfoot has come!
那是谁
Who is that?
看起来可不友善
He doesn't look very happy.
他叫丹恩 是铁丘陵国王
It is Dain, Lord of the Iron Hills.
索林的堂兄
Thorin's cousin.
他俩相像吗
Are they alike?
我觉得他比索林更不理智
I've always found Thorin the more reasonable of the two.
早上好
Good morning.
大家还好吗
How are we all?
我有个小小的提议
I have a wee proposition...
如果不介意我花费一点你们宝贵的时间
...if you wouldn't mind giving me a few moments of your time.
可否考虑一下
Would you consider...
自己滚开
...just sodding off?
所有人
All of you!
马上滚
Right now!
不许后退
Stand fast.
冷静一下 丹恩大王
Come now, Lord Dain.
灰袍甘道夫
Gandalf the Grey.
叫这群乌合之众散了 不然我会让他们血流成河
Tell this rabble to leave, or I'll water the ground with their blood!
矮人 人类和精灵没有必要挑起战争
There is no need for war between Dwarves, Men and Elves.
一大批半兽人正在朝孤山涌来
A legion of Orcs march on the Mountain.
叫你的人冷静
Stand down.
我不会在任何精灵面前冷静
I will not stand down before any Elf.
尤其是这背信弃义的林地精灵
Not least this faithless Woodland sprite.
他一心只想让我的人民遭殃
He wishes nothing but ill upon my people.
如果他选择
If he chooses...
依然和我们作对
...to stand between me and my kin...
我就让他的脑袋开花
...I'll split his pretty head open!
看他是不是还会那样傻笑
See if he's still smirking then.
丹恩 等等
Dain, wait!
让他们推进
Let them advance.
看他们能走多远
See how far they get.
你以为我的威胁是放屁吧
You think I give a dead dog for your threats,
你个尖耳朵小公主
you pointy-eared princess?
你们也听到了 我们上
You hear that, lads? We're on!
好好赏给这些杂种们几锤子
Let's give these bastards a good hammering!
让你的人别动
Stand your men down.
我来对付铁足军团这群乌合之众
I'll deal with Ironfoot and his rabble.
准备好
Right then.
等下再发射
Let's get this done.
派出羊骑兵
Send in the goats.
瑟兰迪尔
Thranduil!
这太疯狂了
This is madness!
嘿 你喜欢这个么 你个老绣花枕头
How do you like that, the old twirley-whirlies?
哈哈 死变态
Ha, ha, you buggers!
地蛇
Were-Worms.
拜托 不要吧
Oh, come on.
前进吧 我的大军
地狱大军已来袭
The hordes of hell are upon us!
至死方休
Fight to the death!
我要出去打仗 谁和我一起去
I'm going over the wall. Who's coming with me?
- 好 - 快点 我们走
- Aye! - Come on, let's go!
- 站住 - 什么
- Stand down. - What?
我们要袖手旁观吗
Are we to do nothing?
我说了 站住
I said, stand down!
精灵们
The Elves.
他们不去战斗吗
Will they not fight?
让他们去死吧
冲啊
Charge!
是
Yes!
挡我者死
甘道夫
Uh, Gandalf?
我们站在这合适吗
Is this a good place to stand?
派出战争野兽
布好阵型
破坏他们的战争机器
他们无法双线作战
现在我们开始行动
进攻河谷镇
阿索格
Azog.
他想断我们的后路
He's trying to cut us off.
所有的人
All of you!
立刻退回河谷镇
Fall back to Dale!
快
Now!
到镇里去
To the city!
比尔博 这边
Bilbo! This Way!
西格丽特
Sigrid!
蒂尔达
Tilda!
我的孩子 他们在哪里
My children! Where are my children?
我看见了 他们之前在老集市
I saw them! They were down in the old market!
老集市
The market?
那现在又在哪里
Where are they now?
蒂尔达 西格丽特
Tilda! Sigrid!
巴德 半兽人涌进了堤道
Bard! Orcs are storming over the causeway!
带弓箭手去东面的城墙 抵挡得越久越好
Get the bowmen to the eastern parapet. Hold them off as long as you can.
弓箭手 跟我来
Archers! This way!
半兽人攻占了石街
The Orcs have taken Stone Street!
集市已失手了
The market's overrun!
剩下的人 跟我来
The rest of you follow me!
- 战斗 - 前进
- Charge! - Onward!
决一死战
To the death!
爸爸
Da!
- 这边 - 我们在这边
- Here! - We're down here!
贝恩
Bain!
西格丽特 快趴下
Sigrid! Get down!
听好了
Listen!
我要你们把孩子和女人聚集起来
I need you to gather the women and children.
带他们到大殿去
Take them to the Great Hall...
把门封住
...and barricade the door.
明白吗
You understand?
不管什么原因都别出来
You must not come out for any reason.
我们要和你在一起
We want to stay with you!
听你父亲的话
Show your father some respect.
把他们交给我 大人
You leave it to me, sire.
你听到他说的了
You heard him.
- 我们去大殿 - 阿尔弗雷德
- We make for the Great Hall. - Alfrid!
只有妇孺可以避难
Women and children only.
我要所有男人参战
I need every man fighting.
你务必回来战斗
See that you return.
我保证把他们安全送达 大人
I'll get them to safety, sire.
然后我就马上回来 快起来
Then my sword is yours to command. Get up!
照顾好她们
Look after them.
快点 老太婆
Shift it, granny!
快去大殿
Make for the Great Hall!
都给我让开
Out of my way!
跑不动的就别管了
Abandon the cripples!
他们守不住这座城
矮人也快完蛋了
你个杂种
You buggers!
索林
Thorin
索林在哪里
Where's Thorin?
我们需要他 他在哪里
We need him! Where is he?
让这里血流成河
全部杀光
撤退
Fall back!
从什么时候开始我们不管自己人的死活了
Since when do we forsake our own people?
索林
Thorin...
他们在外面流血牺牲
...they are dying out there.
这山里地洞连着地洞
There are halls beneath halls within this Mountain.
我们可以用来防御
Places we can fortify...
稳固地势 确保安全
...shore up, make safe.
是的
Yes.
没错
Yes...
就是这样
...that is it.
我们得把金子移到更深的地下
We must move the gold further underground...
- 保证它们安全 - 你到底有没有听我说
- ...to safety. - Did you hear me?
丹恩正被敌军包围
Dain is surrounded.
他们快被杀光了 索林
They're being slaughtered, Thorin.
战争总会死人
Many die in war.
人命如草芥
Life is cheap.
失去的那些人远没有宝藏重要
But a treasure such as this cannot be counted in lives lost.
为了金子死多少人都值得
It is worth all the blood we can spend.
你坐在这宏伟的大厅里
You sit here in these vast halls...
头上戴着王冠
...with a crown upon your head...
实际上却比以往任何时候都渺小
...and yet you are lesser now than you have ever been.
不许这样说
Do not speak to me...
好像我还是那个卑微的矮人王
...as if I were some lowly Dwarf Lord...
就像
...as if...
我仍然是
...I were still...
索林
...Thorin...
橡木盾
...Oakenshield.
- 我是你们的国王 - 你一直是我的国王
- I am your king! - You were always my king.
一直以来都是
You used to know that once.
你看不见自己如今变成了什么样子
You cannot see what you have become.
滚
Go.
出去
Get out.
趁我还没杀死你
Before I kill you.
你坐在这
You sit here...
头上戴着王冠
...with a crown upon your head.
比以往任何时候都渺小
You are lesser now than you have ever been.
失去的那些人远没有宝藏重要
But a treasure such as this cannot be counted in lives lost.
那些宝藏带有邪气
A sickness lies upon that treasure.
孤山国王 贪得无厌
The blind ambition of a Mountain King.
难道我不是国王吗
Am I not the king?
这些黄金是我们的
This gold is ours...
也只能属于我们
And ours alone.
储存的财宝
Treasure hoard...
我不会把
I will not part...
任何一个金币分出去
...with a single coin.
他鼠目寸光 只看得到自己的欲望
He could not see beyond his own desire!
好像我还是那个卑微的矮人王
As if I were some lowly Dwarf Lord...
索林·橡木盾
...Thorin Oakenshield.
宝藏的邪气曾让你祖父疯狂
A sickness which drove your grandfather mad.
橡木盾
Thorin Oakenshield.
这是索林
This is Thorin...
索恩之子 索尔之孙
...son of Thrain, son of Thror!
我不是我的祖父
I am not my grandfather.
你是都灵王位的继承人
You are the heir to the Throne of Durin.
他们在外面流血牺牲
They are dying out there.
夺回埃尔波尔
Take back Erebor.
丹恩正被敌军包围
Dain is surrounded.
垂死挣扎
Dying.
被敌军包围
Is surrounded.
垂死挣扎
Dying.
收复你的家园
Take back your homeland.
你变了 索林
You are changed, Thorin.
我不是我的祖父
I am not my grandfather.
财宝真的比自己的名誉还重要吗
Is this treasure truly worth more than your honor?
我不是我的祖父
I am not my grandfather.
这些宝藏会害死你
This treasure will be your death!
撤退
Fall back!
向孤山撤退
Fall back to the Mountain!
后退
Fall back!
他们的死期到了
准备发起最后的进攻
我不会再躲在
I will not hide...
石墙后面了
...behind a wall of stone...
让别人还在外面为我们拼命
...while others fight our battles for us!
这不是我们家族的传统 索林
It is not in my blood, Thorin.
对
No.
绝不是这样
It is not.
我们是都灵的子孙
We are sons of Durin.
身为都灵的后人
And Durin's Folk...
我们不能在战斗中退缩
...do not flee from a fight.
我没有权力再要求你们所有人
I have no right to ask this of any of you.
但你们愿意跟随我
But will you follow me...
最后一次吗
...one last time?
还不到时候 等等 等等
现在 进攻
索林
Thorin.
为了国王
To the king!
冲啊
那些矮人
The Dwarves.
他们在反击
They're rallying.
他们为了国王战斗
They're rallying to their king.
所有愿意抗争到底的人
Any man who wants to give their last...
跟我来
...follow me!
快点 邦博 快起来
Come on, Bombur. Get up.
- 诺力 - 葛罗音
- Nori. - Gloin!
在你身后 兄弟
Right behind you, brother.
我说咱们应该和男人们同生共死 并肩作战
I say we stand with our men in life and in death.
- 我也去 - 拿起武器
- I'm with you. - Arm yourselves.
- 和我们一起吧 - 不 不 不
- Come with us. - No, no, no.
- 放过我这个老太婆吧 - 别害怕
- You leave an old woman be. - Don't be afraid.
我叫你滚开
I said, get off!
是马屁精阿尔弗雷德
Alfrid Lickspittle.
你就是一个懦夫
You are a coward.
"懦夫"
"Coward"?
不是每个男人都有胆子穿女人的束胸衣
Not every man's brave enough to wear a corset.
你不配当男人
You're not a man.
你是个鼠辈
You're a weasel.
丹恩
Dain!
索林
Thorin!
撑住
Hold on!
我来了
I'm coming!
嗨 我说堂弟
Hey, cousin!
怎么这么久才来
What took you so long?
这里的丑八怪太多了 索林
There's too many of these buggers, Thorin.
希望你已经有计划了
I hope you've got a plan.
对
Aye.
我们去干掉他们的头领
We're going to take out their leader.
阿索格
Azog?
我要杀了那头肮脏的东西
I'm gonna kill that piece of filth.
索林 你不能这么做
Thorin, you cannot do this.
你是我们的国王
You're our king.
所以我才要亲自去做
That is why I must do it.
那你计划怎么单枪匹马杀开一条路去渡鸦岭？
And how do you plan to fight your way single-handed to Ravenhill?
停下
Halt!
我有段时间没开过这玩意儿了
It's been a while since I've done this.
去渡鸦岭
To Ravenhill!
抓紧了 伙计
Hold tight, lads.
你们这群疯狂的家伙
You're all mad bastards.
我喜欢
I like it.
希望都灵保佑你们
May Durin save you all.
小心
Watch out!
眼睛看前面 伙计
Eyes front lads!
坚持住
Hold on!
换弹夹
I'm out!
放倒那家伙
Bring it down!
- 射死他 - 射哪里？
- Shoot it! - Where?
瞄准他的咽喉
In his jambags!
这货没有喉咙啊
It doesn't have any jambags!
- 低头 - 奇力
- Duck! - Kili!
快走
Move it!
坚持住 伙计 我来了
Hang on, lads! I'm coming!
波佛 你太帅了
Bofur, you beauty!
- 德瓦林 - 前进
- Dwalin! - Go!
来吧 你这没毛的豪猪
Come on, you hairy hedgepig!
来啊
Come on!
耶
Yeah!
- 耶 - 耶
- Yeah! - Yeah!
座狼
Wargs!
抓紧了 伙计
Hold tight, lads.
更多的来了
There's more coming!
我们载重太多了
We're pulling too much weight.
我们办不到了
We won't make it.
切断缰绳
Cut the tracers.
骑着他们去渡鸦岭
Ride them to Ravenhill.
不 巴林
No, Balin.
我骑不动山羊了
My goat-riding days are over.
都灵保佑你
Durin be with you, brother.
我可会玩这个了
I am too old for this.
驾
Hyah!
冲啊
Onwards!
向前冲
Lead on!
站起来
Get up.
离我远点
Get away from me.
我不听你的命令了
I don't take orders from you.
人民相信你
People trusted you.
他们听你的
They listened to you.
城主的家里有那么多财宝
The master's mantle was there for the taking，
你却都扔光了
and you threw it all away.
为了什么？
For what?
阿尔弗雷德
Alfrid...
你的衬裙露出来了
...your slip is showing.
我们没准儿真能赢
We may yet survive this.
甘道夫
Gandalf!
那是索林
It's Thorin.
跟着菲力和奇力
And Fili, Kili...
还有德瓦林
...and Dwalin.
他带了最勇猛的手下
He's taking his best warriors.
去干什么
To do what?
去取那魔头的脑袋
To cut the head off the snake.
去死吧
Die!
甘道夫
Gandalf!
莱戈拉斯
Legolas.
莱戈拉斯·绿叶
Legolas Greenleaf.
- 还有一队敌军 - 什么？
- There is a second army. - What?
博尔格带领着冈达巴山的半兽人 就快赶到这里了
Bolg leads a force of Gundabad Orcs. They are almost upon us.
冈达巴山
Gundabad.
这就是他们的全部计划
This was their plan all along.
阿索格牵制我们的主力 博尔格趁机从北边进攻
Azog engages our forces, then Bolg sweeps in from the North.
什么 从北方
What...The North?
哪边是北
Where is the North...
- 到底在哪里 - 在渡鸦岭
- exactly? - Ravenhill.
渡鸦岭
Ravenhill?
索林还在那里
Thorin is up there.
菲力和奇力 他们都在上面
And Fili and Kili. They're all up there.
他在哪儿
Where is he?
看起来空无一人
It looks empty.
我认为阿索格逃了
I think Azog has fled.
我看未必
I don't think so.
菲力
Fili...
带上你弟弟
...take your brother.
搜寻整座塔
Scout out the towers.
保持低调 隐匿行踪
Keep low and out of sight.
如果你发现了什么
If you see something...
立即回来报告 不要逗留
...report back. Do not engage.
- 明白吗 - 我们有伴了
- Do you understand? - We have company.
哥布林佣兵
Goblin mercenaries.
不到一百来个
No more than a hundred.
我们来搞定 你们快走
We'll take care of them. Go!
快走
Go!
来啊
Come on!
召回部队
Recall your company.
陛下 把军队派遣到渡鸦岭吧 矮人要被突袭了
My lord, dispatch this force to Ravenhill. The Dwarves are about to be overrun.
得有人警告索林
Thorin must be warned.
那去警告他啊
By all means, warn him.
我们精灵在这片被诅咒的地方流了太多血 到此为止
I have spent enough Elvish blood in defense of this accursed land. No more.
瑟兰迪尔
Thranduil?
我去
I'll go.
别傻了
Don't be ridiculous.
你不会成功的
You'll never make it.
为什么
Why not?
因为他们会看见你过来 并杀了你
Because they will see you coming and kill you.
不 他们不会
No, they won't.
他们不会看见我
They won't see me.
绝对不行
It's out of the question.
我不准许
I won't allow it.
我不是在请求你准许 甘道夫
I'm not asking you to allow it, Gandalf.
你不能离开
你们不能见死不救
You will not turn away.
这次不行
Not this time.
别挡我的路
Get out of my way.
矮人会被屠杀殆尽
The Dwarves will be slaughtered.
是 他们会死
Yes, they will die.
今天
Today...
或明天
...tomorrow...
一年之后或百年之后
...one year hence, a hundred years from now.
那又有什么关系
What does it matter?
他们只是凡人
They are mortal.
你以为你的生命比他们更高贵
You think your life is worth more than theirs...
可是你心中根本没有爱
...when there is no love in it?
你心里根本没有爱
There is no love in you.
你又懂什么爱了
What do you know of love?
什么也不懂
Nothing.
你对那个矮人的感情不是真的
What you feel for that Dwarf is not real.
你以为那是爱
You think it is love?
那你准备好为爱而死了吗
Are you ready to die for it?
如果你要伤害她
那你要先杀了我
我和你一起去
I will go with you.
推
Push!
你的斧子掉了
By Durin, you've lost your ax.
不 他没掉
No, he's not.
还给你 堂兄
There you go, cousin.
你知道你该插在哪里
You know where you can stick that.
别过去
Hey. Stay here.
继续往下搜查
Search the lower levels.
这个我来对付
I've got this.
那个肮脏的半兽人在哪
Where is that Orc filth?
索林
Thorin.
比尔博
Bilbo.
你们必须离开这里 赶快
You have to leave here. Now.
阿索格还有一支军队 将从北面进攻
Azog has an army attacking from the North.
瞭望塔将会完全被包围
This watchtower will be surrounded.
- 那时就没有退路了 - 要得手了
- With no way out. - We are so close.
那个半兽人杂碎就在里面 要我说直接冲进去
That Orc scum is in there. I say we push on.
不 那正是他的目的
No. That's what he wants.
引诱我们进去
He wants to draw us in.
这是个圈套
This is a trap.
找到菲力和奇力 叫他们回来
Find Fili and Kili. Call them back.
索林 真要这么做吗
Thorin, are you sure about this?
快去
Do it.
我们择日再战
We'll live to fight another day.
这个最先死
然后是他的兄弟
接着是你 橡木盾
你是最后一个
快走
Go.
快跑啊
Run!
你的血脉就此终结
奇力
Kili!
索林
Thorin.
索林 不要
Thorin. No.
全部杀光
不
No.
奇力
Kili.
去杀了他
干掉他
奇力
Kili!
塔瑞尔
Tauriel!
奇力
Kili.
不要
No!
不
塔瑞尔
Tauriel!
巨鹰来了
The Eagles are coming.
比尔博
Bilbo.
别动 别动 躺好了
Don't move. Don't move. Lie still.
很高兴你在这里
I'm glad you are here.
我希望死前能跟你重修旧好
I wish to part from you in friendship.
不
No.
你会活得好好的 索林
You are not going anywhere, Thorin.
你会活下去的
You're going to live.
我要收回
I would take back...
在城墙上对你说的话和做的事
...my words and my deeds at the Gate.
你做了真正的朋友才会做的事
You did what only a true friend would do.
原谅我
Forgive me.
我被贪欲蒙蔽了双眼
I was too blind to see it.
我非常抱歉
I am so sorry...
把你卷入这些险境
...that I have led you into such peril.
不 我很高兴能跟你有难同当 索林
No, I'm glad to have shared in your perils, Thorin.
每一次都是
Each and every one of them.
这远超过任何巴金斯家人所应得
It is far more than any Baggins deserves.
再见了
Farewell...
飞贼先生
...Master Burglar.
回去看你的书
Go back to your books.
享受你的座椅
And your armchair.
种你的树
Plant your trees.
看着它们成长
Watch them grow.
如果更多的人
If more people...
珍视家园
...valued home...
胜过黄金
...above gold...
那这个世界会更美好
...this world would be a merrier place.
不 不 不 不 不 不
No. No, no, no. No.
索林 索林 我不准你死
Thorin. Thorin, don't you dare.
索林
Thorin.
索林 索林 坚持住
Thorin. Thorin, hold on.
你要挺住
Hold on, please.
你看 巨鹰
The Eagles...
巨鹰 巨鹰来帮忙了
The Eagles... The Eagles are here.
索林
Thorin?
鹰
The Ea...
我不能回去了
I cannot go back.
你要到哪里去
Where will you go?
我还不知道
I do not know.
去北方吧
Go north.
找到登丹人
Find the Dúnedain.
那里有一个年轻的游侠 你应该见见他
There's a young Ranger amongst them. You should meet him.
他的父亲阿拉松是个好人
His father, Arathorn, was a good man.
他的儿子
His son...
将来也会是个伟人
...might grow to be a great one.
他叫什么名字
What is his name?
别人都叫他神行客
He's known in the wild as Strider.
他真实的姓名
His true name...
你得自己去发现
...you must discover for yourself.
莱戈拉斯
Legolas.
你母亲很爱你
Your mother loved you.
超越任何人
More than anyone.
胜过自己的生命
More than life.
他们要埋葬他
They want to bury him.
是的
Yes.
如果这就是爱 我宁愿不要
If this is love, I do not want it.
把它从我这收回吧
Take it from me.
求你了
Please.
为什么会如此令人心碎
Why does it hurt so much?
因为这是真心的
Because it was real.
国王殁了
The king is dead.
国王万岁
Long live the king!
今晚这里会大设宴席
There is to be a great feast tonight.
人们歌功颂德 故事将会流传
Songs will be sung. Tales will be told.
索林·橡木盾
And Thorin Oakenshield...
将会成为一个传奇
...will pass into legend.
我知道你们肯定会那样称颂他
I know that's how you must honor him.
但对我而言 他从来都不是那样
But to me, he was never that.
他是
He was...
对我而言
To me...
他是
...he was...
我看我还是悄悄地离开好了 请替我向其他人告别
I'll slip quietly away. Will you tell the others I said goodbye?
你可以亲自和他们说
You can tell them yourself.
以后你们有谁再从袋底洞路过
If any of you are ever passing Bag End, uh...
下午茶四点开始
...tea is at 4.
绝对管够
There's plenty of it.
随时欢迎你们到来
You are welcome anytime.
不用敲门了
Don't bother knocking.
到了夏尔的边界了
Ah, the borders of the Shire.
我们就在这里分开吧
It is here I must leave you.
真遗憾
That's a shame.
我喜欢一路上
I quite liked having...
有巫师在身边陪伴
...a Wizard around.
他们似乎总能带来好运气
Seems they bring good luck.
你不会真以为 你这一路的冒险和逃脱
You don't really suppose, do you, that all your adventures and escapes...
仅仅是因为运气好吧
...were managed by mere luck?
魔力指环不能轻易使用 比尔博
Magic rings should not be used lightly, Bilbo.
不要当我是傻子
Don't take me for a fool.
我知道你在哥布林的地道里捡到了一枚
I know you found one in the Goblin tunnels.
从那时起我就一直盯着你
And I've kept my eye on you ever since.
好吧 谢天谢地
Well, thank goodness.
再会了 甘道夫
Farewell, Gandalf.
再会
Farewell.
你
You, uh...
你不必担心那个戒指 战斗时它从我的口袋里掉了出来
You needn't worry about that ring. Fell out of my pocket during the battle.
找不到了
I lost it.
你是一个品行高尚的人 巴金斯先生
You're a very fine person, Mr. Baggins.
我非常欣赏你
And I'm very fond of you.
但毕竟你只是个小人物
But you're only quite a little fellow...
而这世界大得很
...in a wide world after all.
等一下 那是我母亲的嫁妆盒
Wait a minute, that's my mother's glory box.
那是 我的餐桌椅
And that's my dining chair.
嘿 把那个给我放下
Ah... Put that pouf down!
这是怎么回事
What is going on?
你好 比尔博先生
Hello, Mr. Bilbo.
你不应该出现在这里的
You're not supposed to be here.
你什么意思
What do you mean?
因为你已经被认定为死亡了
On account of you being presumed dead.
我没死
I am not dead.
认定不成立
Presumed or otherwise.
我不确定这样行不行
I'm not sure that's permitted.
比尔博先生
Mr. Bilbo!
还有谁 出价二十一块
Twenty-one! Any advance on 21?
二十一块还有谁
Any advance on 21?
卖给博尔吉太太了
Ha, ha! Sold to Mrs. Bolger.
可以给小胖墩垫脚用
Somewhere for Fatty to put his feet on.
这里还有一些工艺品
Any bids for this?
纯正的夏尔制造
This is Shire-made.
绝对没有一件是矮人的仿制品
No Dwarvish reproductions here.
停下
Stop!
- 这里有些误会 - 你是谁
- There's been a mistake! - Who are you?
你什么意思 问我是谁
What do you mean who am I?
你肯定清楚的知道我是谁
You know perfectly well who I am...
罗贝利亚·塞克维拉·巴金斯
...Lobelia Sackville-Baggins.
这是我的家
This is my home.
那些是我的勺子 非常感谢
And those are my spoons. Thank you very much.
- 这太疯狂了 - 让一下
- This is most irregular. - Excuse me.
你失踪已经超过十三个月了
It's been more than 13 months since the disappearance.
如果你是真的
If you are in fact...
比尔博·巴金斯 并且还没有死
...Bilbo Baggins and undeceased...
你能证明吗
...can you prove it?
什么
What?
一些正式的印有你名字在上面的物件就可以
Something official with your name on it would suffice.
好吧 好吧
All right. Right.
这是一份雇佣合同 雇用我作为飞…
A contract of employment as a bur...
别管飞什么的了
Never mind as what.
这里 我的签名
There. My signature.
好的 那么
Yes, well... Uh...
噢 看起来确实是正规文件
Well, it certainly seems to be in order.
是的
Yes.
看来毫无疑问
Seems there can be no doubt.
这个接受你服务的人是谁
Who is this you pledged your service to?
索林·橡木盾
Thorin Oakenshield?
他
He...
他是我的朋友
He was my friend.
不要敲了 谢谢
No, thank you!
我们不想见任何访客 祝寿者
We don't want any more visitors, well-wishers...
或者远亲
...or distant relations!
那如果是
And what about...
非常老的朋友呢
...very old friends?
甘道夫
Gandalf?
比尔博·巴金斯
Bilbo Baggins.
我亲爱的甘道夫
My dear Gandalf!
见到你真好
It's good to see you.
你都111岁了 谁会信呢
One hundred and 11 years old. Who would believe it?
快请 快进来
Come on, come in!
欢迎 欢迎
Welcome. Welcome.